ŇDear boy and PipŐs comrade. I am not a-going fur to tell you my life like a song, or a story-book.
But to give it you short and handy, IŐll put it at once into a mouthful of English. In jail and
out of jail, in jail and out of jail, in jail and out of jail. There, youŐve got it. ThatŐs
my life pretty much, down to such times as I got shipped off, arter Pip stood my friend.
ŇIŐve been done everything to, pretty wellŃexcept hanged. IŐve been locked up
as much as a silver tea-kittle. IŐve been carted here and carted there,
and put out of this town, and put out of that town, and stuck in the stocks,
and whipped and worried and drove. IŐve no more notion where I was born than you haveŃif
so much. I first become aware of myself down in Essex, a thieving turnips for my living. Summun
had run away from meŃa manŃa tinkerŃand heŐd took the fire with him, and left me wery cold.
ŇI knowŐd my name to be Magwitch, chrisenŐd Abel. How did I know it? Much as I knowŐd the
birdsŐ names in the hedges to be chaffinch, sparrer, thrush. I might have thought it
was all lies together, only as the birdsŐ names come out true, I supposed mine did.
ŇSo fur as I could find, there warnŐt a soul that see young Abel Magwitch,
with us little on him as in him, but wot caught fright at him, and either drove him off,
or took him up. I was took up, took up, took up, to that extent that I regŐlarly growŐd up took up.
ŇThis is the way it was, that when I was a ragged little creetur as much to be pitied as ever I see
(not that I looked in the glass, for there warnŐt many insides of furnished houses known to me),
I got the name of being hardened. ÔThis is a terrible hardened one,Ő they says to prison
wisitors, picking out me. ÔMay be said to live in jails, this boy.Ő Then they looked at me,
and I looked at them, and they measured my head, some on Őem,Ńthey
had better a measured my stomach,Ńand others on Őem giv me tracts what I couldnŐt read, and
made me speeches what I couldnŐt understand. They always went on agen me about the Devil. But what
the Devil was I to do? I must put something into my stomach, mustnŐt I?ŃHowsomever, IŐm a getting
low, and I know whatŐs due. Dear boy and PipŐs comrade, donŐt you be afeerd of me being low.
ŇTramping, begging, thieving, working sometimes when I could,Ńthough that warnŐt as often as you
may think, till you put the question whether you would haŐ been over-ready to give me
work yourselves,Ńa bit of a poacher, a bit of a labourer, a bit of a wagoner, a bit of a haymaker,
a bit of a hawker, a bit of most things that donŐt pay and lead to trouble, I got to be a man. A
deserting soldier in a TravellerŐs Rest, what lay hid up to the chin under a lot of taturs, learnt
me to read; and a travelling Giant what signed his name at a penny a time learnt me to write.
I warnŐt locked up as often now as formerly, but I wore out my good share of key-metal still.
ŇAt Epsom races, a matter of over twenty years ago, I got acquainted wiŐ a man whose skull
IŐd crack wiŐ this poker, like the claw of a lobster, if IŐd got it on this hob. His right
name was Compeyson; and thatŐs the man, dear boy, what you see me a pounding in the ditch,
according to what you truly told your comrade arter I was gone last night.
ŇHe set up fur a gentleman, this Compeyson, and heŐd been to a public boarding-school and
had learning. He was a smooth one to talk, and was a dab at the ways of gentlefolks.
He was good-looking too. It was the night afore the great race, when I found him on the heath,
in a booth that I knowŐd on. Him and some more was a sitting among the tables when I went in,
and the landlord (which had a knowledge of me, and was a sporting one) called him out,
and said, ÔI think this is a man that might suit you,ŐŃmeaning I was.
ŇCompeyson, he looks at me very noticing, and I look at him. He
has a watch and a chain and a ring and a breast-pin and a handsome suit of clothes.
ŇÔTo judge from appearances, youŐre out of luck,Ő says Compeyson to me.
ŇÔYes, master, and IŐve never been in it much.Ő (I had come out of Kingston Jail last
on a vagrancy committal. Not but what it might have been for something else; but it warnŐt.)
ŇÔLuck changes,Ő says Compeyson; Ôperhaps yours is going to change.Ő
ŇI says, ÔI hope it may be so. ThereŐs room.Ő
ŇÔWhat can you do?Ő says Compeyson.
ŇÔEat and drink,Ő I says; Ôif youŐll find the materials.Ő
ŇCompeyson laughed, looked at me again very noticing, giv me five shillings,
and appointed me for next night. Same place. ŇI went to Compeyson next night, same place,
and Compeyson took me on to be his man and pardner. And what was CompeysonŐs business
in which we was to go pardners? CompeysonŐs business was the swindling, handwriting forging,
stolen bank-note passing, and such-like. All sorts of traps as Compeyson could set with his head,
and keep his own legs out of and get the profits from and let another man in for,
was CompeysonŐs business. HeŐd no more heart than a iron file,
he was as cold as death, and he had the head of the Devil afore mentioned.
ŇThere was another in with Compeyson, as was called Arthur,Ńnot as being so chrisenŐd,
but as a surname. He was in a Decline, and was a shadow to look at. Him and Compeyson had been
in a bad thing with a rich lady some years afore, and theyŐd made a pot of money by it;
but Compeyson betted and gamed, and heŐd have run through the kingŐs taxes. So, Arthur was a dying,
and a dying poor and with the horrors on him, and CompeysonŐs wife (which Compeyson kicked mostly)
was a having pity on him when she could, and Compeyson was a having pity on nothing and nobody.
ŇI might a took warning by Arthur, but I didnŐt; and I wonŐt pretend I was partickŐlerŃfor where
Őud be the good on it, dear boy and comrade? So I begun wiŐ Compeyson, and a poor tool I
was in his hands. Arthur lived at the top of CompeysonŐs house (over nigh Brentford it was),
and Compeyson kept a careful account agen him for board and lodging, in case he should ever
get better to work it out. But Arthur soon settled the account. The second or third
time as ever I see him, he come a tearing down into CompeysonŐs parlour late at night,
in only a flannel gown, with his hair all in a sweat, and he says to CompeysonŐs wife, ÔSally,
she really is upstairs alonger me, now, and I canŐt get rid of her. SheŐs all in
white,Ő he says, ÔwiŐ white flowers in her hair, and sheŐs awful mad, and sheŐs got
a shroud hanging over her arm, and she says sheŐll put it on me at five in the morning.Ő
ŇSays Compeyson: ÔWhy, you fool, donŐt you know sheŐs got a living body? And how should she be
up there, without coming through the door, or in at the window, and up the stairs?Ő
ŇÔI donŐt know how sheŐs there,Ő says Arthur,
shivering dreadful with the horrors, Ôbut sheŐs standing in the corner at the foot of the bed,
awful mad. And over where her heartŐs brokeŃyou broke it!ŃthereŐs drops of blood.Ő
ŇCompeyson spoke hardy, but he was always a coward. ÔGo up alonger this drivelling sick
man,Ő he says to his wife, Ôand Magwitch, lend her a hand, will you?Ő But he never come nigh himself.
ŇCompeysonŐs wife and me took him up to bed agen, and he raved most dreadful. ÔWhy look
at her!Ő he cries out. ÔSheŐs a shaking the shroud at me! DonŐt you see her? Look
at her eyes! AinŐt it awful to see her so mad?Ő Next he cries, ÔSheŐll put it on me,
and then IŐm done for! Take it away from her, take it away!Ő And then he catched hold of us,
and kep on a talking to her, and answering of her, till I half believed I see her myself.
ŇCompeysonŐs wife, being used to him, giv him some liquor to get the horrors off, and by and by he
quieted. ÔO, sheŐs gone! Has her keeper been for her?Ő he says. ÔYes,Ő says CompeysonŐs wife. ÔDid
you tell him to lock her and bar her in?Ő ÔYes.Ő ÔAnd to take that ugly thing away from her?Ő ÔYes,
yes, all right.Ő ÔYouŐre a good creetur,Ő he says, ÔdonŐt leave me, whatever you do, and thank you!Ő
ŇHe rested pretty quiet till it might want a few minutes of five,
and then he starts up with a scream, and screams out, ÔHere she is! SheŐs got the shroud again.
SheŐs unfolding it. SheŐs coming out of the corner. SheŐs coming to the bed. Hold me,
both on youŃone of each sideŃdonŐt let her touch me with it. Hah! she missed
me that time. DonŐt let her throw it over my shoulders. DonŐt let her lift me up to get it
round me. SheŐs lifting me up. Keep me down!Ő Then he lifted himself up hard, and was dead.
ŇCompeyson took it easy as a good riddance for both sides. Him and me was soon busy,
and first he swore me (being ever artful) on my own book,Ńthis here little black book,
dear boy, what I swore your comrade on.
ŇNot to go into the things that Compeyson planned,
and I doneŃwhich Őud take a weekŃIŐll simply say to you, dear boy, and PipŐs comrade, that that
man got me into such nets as made me his black slave. I was always in debt to him,
always under his thumb, always a working, always a getting into danger. He was younger than me,
but heŐd got craft, and heŐd got learning, and he overmatched me five hundred times told and
no mercy. My Missis as I had the hard time wiŐŃStop though! I ainŐt brought her inŃÓ
He looked about him in a confused way, as if he had lost his place in the book of his remembrance;
and he turned his face to the fire, and spread his hands broader on his knees,
and lifted them off and put them on again. ŇThere ainŐt no need to go into it,Ó he said,
looking round once more. ŇThe time wiŐ Compeyson was aŐmost as hard a time as ever I had;
that said, allŐs said. Did I tell you as I was tried, alone, for misdemeanor,
while with Compeyson?Ó I answered, No.
ŇWell!Ó he said, ŇI was, and got convicted. As to took up on suspicion, that was twice
or three times in the four or five year that it lasted; but evidence was wanting. At last,
me and Compeyson was both committed for felony,Ńon a charge of putting
stolen notes in circulation,Ńand there was other charges behind. Compeyson says to me,
ÔSeparate defences, no communication,Ő and that was all. And I was so miserable poor,
that I sold all the clothes I had, except what hung on my back, afore I could get Jaggers.
ŇWhen we was put in the dock, I noticed first of all what a gentleman Compeyson looked,
wiŐ his curly hair and his black clothes and his white pocket-handkercher, and what a common sort
of a wretch I looked. When the prosecution opened and the evidence was put short,
aforehand, I noticed how heavy it all bore on me, and how light on him.
When the evidence was giv in the box, I noticed how it was always me that had come forŐard,
and could be swore to, how it was always me that the money had been paid to, how it was
always me that had seemed to work the thing and get the profit. But when the defence come on,
then I see the plan plainer; for, says the counsellor for Compeyson, ÔMy lord and gentlemen,
here you has afore you, side by side, two persons as your eyes can separate wide;
one, the younger, well brought up, who will be spoke to as such; one, the elder, ill brought up,
who will be spoke to as such; one, the younger, seldom if ever seen in these here transactions,
and only suspected; tŐother, the elder, always seen in Őem and always wiŐ his guilt brought home.
Can you doubt, if there is but one in it, which is the one, and, if there is two in it, which is much
the worst one?Ő And such-like. And when it come to character, warnŐt it Compeyson as had been to
the school, and warnŐt it his schoolfellows as was in this position and in that, and warnŐt it
him as had been knowŐd by witnesses in such clubs and societies, and nowt to his disadvantage? And
warnŐt it me as had been tried afore, and as had been knowŐd up hill and down dale in Bridewells
and Lock-Ups! And when it come to speech-making, warnŐt it Compeyson as could speak to Őem wiŐ
his face dropping every now and then into his white pocket-handkercher,Ńah! and wiŐ verses
in his speech, too,Ńand warnŐt it me as could only say, ÔGentlemen, this man at my side is a
most precious rascalŐ? And when the verdict come, warnŐt it Compeyson as was recommended to mercy
on account of good character and bad company, and giving up all the information he could agen me,
and warnŐt it me as got never a word but Guilty? And when I says to Compeyson, ÔOnce out of this
court, IŐll smash that face of yourn!Ő ainŐt it Compeyson as prays the Judge to be protected, and
gets two turnkeys stood betwixt us? And when weŐre sentenced, ainŐt it him as gets seven year, and me
fourteen, and ainŐt it him as the Judge is sorry for, because he might a done so well, and ainŐt it
me as the Judge perceives to be a old offender of wiolent passion, likely to come to worse?Ó
He had worked himself into a state of great excitement, but he checked it,
took two or three short breaths, swallowed as often, and stretching out his hand
towards me said, in a reassuring manner, ŇI ainŐt a-going to be low, dear boy!Ó
He had so heated himself that he took out his handkerchief and
wiped his face and head and neck and hands, before he could go on.
ŇI had said to Compeyson that IŐd smash that face of his, and I swore Lord smash mine! to
do it. We was in the same prison-ship, but I couldnŐt get at him for long,
though I tried. At last I come behind him and hit him on the cheek to turn him round and get
a smashing one at him, when I was seen and seized. The black-hole of that ship warnŐt a strong one,
to a judge of black-holes that could swim and dive. I escaped to the shore, and I was
a hiding among the graves there, envying them as was in Őem and all over, when I first see my boy!Ó
He regarded me with a look of affection that made him almost abhorrent to me again,
though I had felt great pity for him.
ŇBy my boy, I was giv to understand as Compeyson was out on them marshes too. Upon my soul,
I half believe he escaped in his terror, to get quit of me, not knowing it was me as had got
ashore. I hunted him down. I smashed his face. ÔAnd now,Ő says I Ôas the worst thing I can do,
caring nothing for myself, IŐll drag you back.Ő And IŐd have swum off,
towing him by the hair, if it had come to that, and IŐd a got him aboard without the soldiers.
ŇOf course heŐd much the best of it to the last,Ńhis character
was so good. He had escaped when he was made half wild by me and my murderous intentions;
and his punishment was light. I was put in irons, brought to trial again,
and sent for life. I didnŐt stop for life, dear boy and PipŐs comrade, being here.Ó
He wiped himself again, as he had done before, and then slowly took his tangle of tobacco from his
pocket, and plucked his pipe from his button-hole, and slowly filled it, and began to smoke.
ŇIs he dead?Ó I asked, after a silence.
ŇIs who dead, dear boy?Ó
ŇCompeyson.Ó
ŇHe hopes I am, if heŐs alive,
you may be sure,Ó with a fierce look. ŇI never heerd no more of him.Ó
Herbert had been writing with his pencil in the cover of a book. He softly pushed
the book over to me, as Provis stood smoking with his eyes on the fire, and I read in it:Ń
ŇYoung HavishamŐs name was Arthur. Compeyson
is the man who professed to be Miss HavishamŐs lover.Ó
I shut the book and nodded slightly to Herbert, and put the book by;
but we neither of us said anything, and both looked at Provis as he stood smoking
by the fire. Chapter 43.